<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_layer_shell_v1">
  <copyright>
    SPDX-FileCopyrightText: © 2025 Isaac Freund
    SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
    of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to
    deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the
    rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or
    sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
    furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
    AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS
    IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="layer shell support for river">
    This protocol allows the river-window-management-v1 window manager to
    support the wlr-layer-shell-v1 protocol.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended", "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.
  </description>

  <interface name="river_layer_shell_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="river layer shell global interface">
      This global interface should only be advertised to the client if the
      river_window_manager_v1 global is also advertised. Binding this interface
      indicates that the window manager supports layer shell.

      If the window manager does not bind this interface, the compositor should
      not allow clients to map layer surfaces. This can be achieved by
      closing layer surfaces immediately.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="object_already_created" value="0"
        summary="the layer_shell_output/seat object was already created."/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_layer_shell_v1 object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the
        river_layer_shell_v1 object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_output">
      <description summary="get layer shell output state">
        It is a protocol error to make this request more than once for a given
        river_output_v1 object.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="river_layer_shell_output_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="river_output_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_seat">
      <description summary="get layer shell seat state">
        It is a protocol error to make this request more than once for a given
        river_seat_v1 object.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="river_layer_shell_seat_v1"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="river_seat_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="river_layer_shell_output_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="layer shell output state">
      The lifetime of this object is tied to the corresponding river_output_v1.
      This object is made inert when the river_output_v1.removed event is sent
      and should be destroyed.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the
        river_layer_shell_output_v1 object and that it may be safely destroyed.

        This request should be made after the river_output_v1.removed event is
        received to complete destruction of the output.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="non_exclusive_area">
      <description summary="area left after subtracting exclusive zones">
        This event indicates the area of the output remaining after subtracting
        the exclusive zones of layer surfaces. Exclusive zones are a hint, the
        window manager is free to ignore this area hint if it wishes.

        The x and y values are in the global coordinate space, not relative to
        the position of the output.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <request name="set_default">
      <description summary="Set default output for layer surfaces">
        Mark this output as the default for new layer surfaces which do not
        request a specific output themselves. This request overrides any
        previous set_default request on any river_layer_shell_output_v1 object.

        If no set_default request is made or if the default output is destroyed,
        the default output is undefined until the next set_default request.

        This request modifies window management state and may only be made as
        part of a manage sequence, see the river_window_manager_v1 description.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="river_layer_shell_seat_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="layer shell seat state">
      The lifetime of this object is tied to the corresponding river_seat_v1.
      This object is made inert when the river_seat_v1.removed event is sent and
      should be destroyed.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the
        river_layer_shell_seat_v1 object and that it may be safely destroyed.

        This request should be made after the river_seat_v1.removed event is
        received to complete destruction of the seat.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="focus_exclusive">
      <description summary="">
        A layer shell surface will be given exclusive keyboard focus at the end
        of the manage sequence in which this event is sent. The window manager
        may want to update window decorations or similar to indicate that no
        window is focused.

        Until the focus_non_exclusive or focus_none event is sent, all window
        manager requests to change focus are ignored.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_non_exclusive">
      <description summary="">
        A layer shell surface will be given non-exclusive keyboard focus at the
        end of the manage sequence in which this event is sent. The window
        manager may want to update window decorations or similar to indicate
        that no window is focused.

        The window manager continues to control focus and may choose to focus a
        different window/shell surface at any time. If the window manager sets
        focus during the same manage sequence in which this event is sent, the
        layer surface will not be focused.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="focus_none">
      <description summary="">
        No layer shell surface will have keyboard focus at the end of the manage
        sequence in which this event is sent. The window manager may want to
        return focus to whichever window last had focus, for example.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
