<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_xkb_bindings_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2025 The River Developers

    Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
    purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
    copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
    WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN ACTION
    OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF OR IN
    CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="define xkbcommon-based key bindings">
    This protocol allows the river-window-management-v1 window manager to
    define key bindings in terms of xkbcommon keysyms and other configurable
    properties.

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended", "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can only
    be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="river_xkb_bindings_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="xkbcommon bindings global interface">
      This global interface should only be advertised to the client if the
      river_window_manager_v1 global is also advertised.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_xkb_bindings_v1 object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the
        river_xkb_bindings_v1 object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xkb_binding">
      <description summary="define a new xkbcommon key binding">
        Define a key binding for the given seat in terms of an xkbcommon keysym
        and other configurable properties.

        The new key binding is not enabled until initial configuration is
        completed and the enable request is made during a manage sequence.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="river_seat_v1"/>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="river_xkb_binding_v1"/>
      <arg name="keysym" type="uint" summary="an xkbcommon keysym"/>
      <arg name="modifiers" type="uint" enum="river_seat_v1.modifiers"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="river_xkb_binding_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="configure a xkb key binding, receive trigger events">
      This object allows the window manager to configure a xkbcommon key binding
      and receive events when the key binding is triggered.

      The new key binding is not enabled until the enable request is made during
      a manage sequence.

      Normally, all key events are sent to the surface with keyboard focus by
      the compositor. Key events that trigger a key binding are not sent to the
      surface with keyboard focus.

      If multiple key bindings would be triggered by a single physical key event
      on the compositor side, it is compositor policy which key binding(s) will
      receive press/release events or if all of the matched key bindings receive
      press/release events.

      Key bindings might be matched by the same physical key event due to shared
      keysym and modifiers. The layout override feature may also cause the same
      physical key event to trigger two key bindings with different keysyms and
      different layout overrides configured.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the xkb binding object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the xkb key
        binding object and that it may be safely destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_layout_override">
      <description summary="override currently active xkb layout">
        Specify an xkb layout that should be used to translate key events for
        the purpose of triggering this key binding irrespective of the currently
        active xkb layout.

        The layout argument is a 0-indexed xkbcommon layout number for the
        keyboard that generated the key event.

        If this request is never made, the currently active xkb layout of the
        keyboard that generated the key event will be used.

        This request modifies window management state and may only be made as
        part of a manage sequence, see the river_window_manager_v1 description.
      </description>
      <arg name="layout" type="uint" summary="0-indexed xkbcommon layout"/>
    </request>

    <request name="enable">
      <description summary="enable the key binding">
        This request should be made after all initial configuration has been
        completed and the window manager wishes the key binding to be able to be
        triggered.

        This request modifies window management state and may only be made as
        part of a manage sequence, see the river_window_manager_v1 description.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="disable">
      <description summary="disable the key binding">
        This request may be used to temporarily disable the key binding. It may
        be later re-enabled with the enable request.

        This request modifies window management state and may only be made as
        part of a manage sequence, see the river_window_manager_v1 description.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="pressed">
      <description summary="the key triggering the binding has been pressed">
        This event indicates that the physical key triggering the binding has
        been pressed.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.

        The compositor should wait for the manage sequence to complete before
        processing further input events. This allows the window manager client
        to, for example, modify key bindings and keyboard focus without racing
        against future input events. The window manager should of course respond
        as soon as possible as the capacity of the compositor to buffer incoming
        input events is finite.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="released">
      <description summary="the key triggering the binding has been released">
        This event indicates that the physical key triggering the binding has
        been released.

        Releasing the modifiers for the binding without releasing the "main"
        physical key that produces the bound keysym does not trigger the release
        event. This event is sent when the "main" key is released, even if the
        modifiers have changed since the pressed event.

        This event will be followed by a manage_start event after all other new
        state has been sent by the server.

        The compositor should wait for the manage sequence to complete before
        processing further input events. This allows the window manager client
        to, for example, modify key bindings and keyboard focus without racing
        against future input events. The window manager should of course respond
        as soon as possible as the capacity of the compositor to buffer incoming
        input events is finite.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
