<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_layout_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2020 Leon Henrik Plickat

    Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
    purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
    copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
    WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
    ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
    OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zriver_layout_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="receive layout requests">
      A global factory for objects that receive layout request from the compositor.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_layout_manager object">
        This request indicates that the client will not use the
        river_layout_manager object any more. Objects that have been created
        through this instance are not affected.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="get_river_layout">
      <description summary="create a layout object">
        This creates a new river_layout object.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="zriver_layout_v1"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zriver_layout_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="receive and respond to river layout requests">
      This interface allows clients to receive layout requests from the
      compositor and subsequently change the position and dimensions of
      individual views.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_layout object">
        This request indicates that the client will not use the river_layout
        object any more.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="layout_request">
      <description summary="the compositors layout may be changed">
        The compositor raises this event to tell the client that it requires a
        layout for a set amount of views on an output.

        Layouts are logically a strictly linear list. Views are only
        identifiable by their index, which resembles the logical position in the
        layout. It is at minimum 0, which corresponds to the first view, and at
        maximum one less than the total amount of views in the layout, which
        corresponds to the last view.

        The useable area of the output indicates the space in which the client
        can safely position views without interfering with desktop widgets such
        as panels. The client may ignore these. The position and dimensions of
        the useable area are given in output local coordinates per XDG-output
        protocol extensions.

        Note that the master area related values are simply proposals and can
        safely be ignored by the client.

        The serial of this event is used to identify subsequent events and
        request as belonging to this layout request. Beware that the client
        might need to handle multiple layout requests at the same time.
      </description>
      <arg name="view_amount" type="uint" summary="amount of views which are part of the layout"/>
      <arg name="m_amount" type="uint" summary="proposed views in the master area"/>
      <arg name="m_fact" type="fixed" summary="proposed master area factor"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="x coordinate of useable area on output"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="y coordinate of useable area on output"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="width of useable area on output"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="height of useable area on output"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of request"/>
    </event>

    <event name="advertise_view">
      <description summary="make layout client aware of view">
        This event is raised by the compositor after a request_layout event,
        whether the layout request has been ack'ed by the client or not.
        It contains additional information about one of the views that are part
        of the requested layout.

        The view is identified by its index, which resembles its logical
        position in the layout. It is at minimum 0, which corresponds to the
        first view, and at maximum one less than the total amount of views in
        the layout, which corresponds to the last view.

        It is guaranteed that every view in the layout will be advertised
        exactly once, in an undefined order.

        A client not interested in the additional information may ignore this event.

        The serial is the same as that of the layout request this event belongs to.
      </description>
      <arg name="index" type="uint" summary="index of view in layout"/>
      <arg name="tag_set" type="uint" summary="bit field, active tags of view"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string" summary="view app-id"/>
      <arg name="title" type="string" summary="view title"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="current x coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="current y coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="current width of view"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="current height of view"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout request"/>
    </event>

    <event name="advertise_done">
      <description summary="all views have been advertised">
        The compositor raises this event when it has advertised all views that
        are part of the requested layout, whether the client has ack'ed the
        layout request or not.

        A client not interested in the additional information may ignore this event.

        The serial is the same as that of the layout request this event belongs to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout request"/>
    </event>

    <request name="ack_layout_request">
      <description summary="ack a layout request">
        The client may use this to signal the compositor that it wants generate
        the requested layout. The first client to send this request gains the
        layout authority, all other clients will be ignored.

        Beware that clients will not be informed whether they have layout
        authority or not and are expected to send their layout "blindly". This
        is due to this protocol extension being designed to avoid roundtrips.

        A client may not respond to a layout request in any way without first
        ack'ing it. However ack'ing does not force the client to send any
        further responses to the layout request of this serial, in which case
        the clients layout authority will silently time out with no feedback.

        The serial is used to identify the layout request this request is a
        response to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout request"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_view_dimensions">
      <description summary="propose view dimensions">
        A client may use this to propose changing the position and dimensions of
        a view in the layout.

        The view is identified by its index, which resembles its logical
        position in the layout. It is at minimum 0, which corresponds to the
        first view, and at maximum one less than the total amount of views in
        the layout, which corresponds to the last view.

        It is not necessary to propose changes for every view in the layout.
        The position and dimensions of left-over views will be determined by the
        compositor.

        This request may be send before the view of the index has been
        advertised by the compositor.

        Dimensions are in output local coordinates per XDG-output protocol
        extensions.

        The serial is used to identify the layout request this request is a
        response to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout request"/>
      <arg name="index" type="uint" summary="index of view in layout"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="x coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="y coordinate of view"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint" summary="width of view"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint" summary="height of view"/>
    </request>

    <request name="commit">
      <description summary="commit a layout request">
        The client may use this to signal the compositor that it has finished
        proposing view dimensions for the requested layout.

        The client will loose layout authority, if it had it.

        Sending this event irrevocably marks the layout as finished. The client
        may not send any other responses to the layout request.

        Beware that the compositor may silently ignore the layout, even if the
        client had the layout authority.

        The serial is used to identify the layout request this request is a
        response to.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of layout request"/>
    </request>

  </interface>
</protocol>
