<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_input_management_v1">
  <copyright>
    SPDX-FileCopyrightText: © 2025 Isaac Freund
    SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
    of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to
    deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the
    rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or
    sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
    furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
    all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
    AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS
    IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="configure input devices">
    This protocol supports creating/destroying seats, assigning input devices to
    seats, and configuring input devices (e.g. setting keyboard repeat rate).

    The key words "must", "must not", "required", "shall", "shall not",
    "should", "should not", "recommended", "may", and "optional" in this
    document are to be interpreted as described in IETF RFC 2119.
  </description>

  <interface name="river_input_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="input manager global interface">
      Input manager global interface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_destroy" value="0"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="stop">
      <description summary="stop sending events">
        This request indicates that the client no longer wishes to receive
        events on this object.

        The Wayland protocol is asynchronous, which means the server may send
        further events until the stop request is processed. The client must wait
        for a river_input_manager_v1.finished event before destroying this
        object.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="finished">
      <description summary="the server has finished with the input manager">
        This event indicates that the server will send no further events on this
        object. The client should destroy the object. See
        river_input_manager_v1.destroy for more information.
      </description>
    </event>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the river_input_manager_v1 object">
        This request should be called after the finished event has been received
        to complete destruction of the object.

        It is a protocol error to make this request before the finished event
        has been received.

        If a client wishes to destroy this object it should send a
        river_input_manager_v1.stop request and wait for a
        river_input_manager_v1.finished event. Once the finished event is
        received it is safe to destroy this object and any other objects created
        through this interface.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="create_seat">
      <description summary="create a new seat">
        Create a new seat with the given name. Has no effect if a seat with the
        given name already exists.

        The default seat with name "default" always exists and does not need to
        be explicitly created.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy_seat">
      <description summary="destroy a seat">
        Destroy the seat with the given name. Has no effect if a seat with the
        given name does not exist.

        The default seat with name "default" cannot be destroyed and attempting
        to destroy it will have no effect.

        Any input devices assigned to the destroyed seat at the time of
        destruction are assigned to the default seat.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <event name="input_device">
      <description summary="new input device">
        A new input device has been created.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="river_input_device_v1"/>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="river_input_device_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="an input device">
      An input device represents a physical keyboard, mouse, touchscreen, or
      drawing tablet tool. It is assigned to exactly one seat at a time.
      By default, all input devices are assigned to the default seat.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="invalid_repeat_info" value="0"/>
      <entry name="invalid_scroll_factor" value="1"/>
      <entry name="invalid_map_to_rectangle" value="2"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the input device object">
        This request indicates that the client will no longer use the input
        device object and that it may be safely destroyed.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="the input device is removed">
        This event indicates that the input device has been removed.

        The server will send no further events on this object and ignore any
        request (other than river_input_device_v1.destroy) made after this event is
        sent. The client should destroy this object with the
        river_input_device_v1.destroy request to free up resources.
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="type">
      <entry name="keyboard" value="0"/>
      <entry name="pointer" value="1"/>
      <entry name="touch" value="2"/>
      <entry name="tablet" value="3"/>
    </enum>

    <event name="type">
      <description summary="the type of the input device">
        The type of the input device. This event is sent once when the
        river_input_device_v1 object is created. The device type cannot
        change during the lifetime of the object.
      </description>
      <arg name="type" type="uint" enum="type"/>
    </event>

    <event name="name">
      <description summary="the name of the input device">
        The name of the input device. This event is sent once when the
        river_input_device_v1 object is created. The device name cannot
        change during the lifetime of the object.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string"/>
    </event>

    <request name="assign_to_seat">
      <description summary="assign the input device to a seat">
        Assign the input device to a seat. All input devices not explicitly
        assigned to a seat are considered assigned to the default seat.

        Has no effect if a seat with the given name does not exist.
      </description>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="name of the seat"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_repeat_info">
      <description summary="set keyboard repeat rate and delay">
        Set repeat rate and delay for a keyboard input device. Has no effect if
        the device is not a keyboard.

        Negative values for either rate or delay are illegal. A rate of zero
        will disable any repeating (regardless of the value of delay).
      </description>
      <arg name="rate" type="int" summary="rate in key repeats per second"/>
      <arg name="delay" type="int" summary="delay in milliseconds"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_scroll_factor">
      <description summary="set scroll factor">
        Set the scroll factor for a pointer input device. Has no effect if the
        device is not a pointer.

        For example, a factor of 0.5 will make scrolling twice as slow while a
        factor of 3.0 will make scrolling 3 times as fast.

        Setting a scroll factor less than 0 is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="factor" type="fixed"/>
    </request>

    <request name="map_to_output">
      <description summary="map input device to the given output">
        Map the input device to the given output. Has no effect if the device is
        not a pointer, touch, or tablet device.

        If mapped to both an output and a rectangle, the rectangle has priority.

        Passing null clears an existing mapping.
      </description>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>

    <request name="map_to_rectangle">
      <description summary="map input device to the given rectangle">
        Map the input device to the given rectangle in the global compositor
        coordinate space. Has no effect if the device is not a pointer, touch,
        or tablet device.

        If mapped to both an output and a rectangle, the rectangle has priority.

        Width and height must be greater than or equal to 0.

        Passing 0 for width or height clears an existing mapping.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
