<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="river_control_unstable_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright 2020 Isaac Freund

    Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
    purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
    copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
    WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
    ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
    OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="zriver_control_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="run compositor commands">
      This interface allows clients to run compositor commands and receive a
      success/failure response with a failure message if needed.
    </description>

    <request name="run_command">
      <description summary="run a compositor command">
        A complete list of commands will be found in the man page for the
        compositor.
      </description>
      <arg name="command" type="array" summary="the command to run as a series
        of null-terminated strings"/>
      <arg name="callback" type="new_id" interface="zriver_command_callback_v1"
        summary="callback object to receive success/error events"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="zriver_command_callback_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="callback object">
      This object is created by the run_command request. Exactly one of the
      success or failure events will be sent.
    </description>

    <event name="success">
      <description summary="command successful">
        Send when the command has been successfully received and validated by
        the server and will be carried out.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="failure">
      <description summary="command failed">
        Sent when the command could not be carried out. This could be due to
        sending a non-existent command, no command, not enough arguments, too
        many arguments, invalid arguments, etc.
      </description>
      <arg name="failure_message" type="string"
        summary="a message explaining why failure occurred"/>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
